Hugh S. Taylor Papers, 1911-1972: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Hugh S. Taylor Papers
1911-1972
C0563
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
13 linear feet 5 archival boxes, 4 record center cartons, 1 oversize flat box, 2 large flat boxes, 1 small box 1 tube
Taylor, Hugh S. (Hugh Stott), 1890-1974.
Consists of articles, correspondence, and printed matter of Hugh S.Taylor, chairman of the Princeton Chemistry Department (1926-1951) and dean of the graduate school (1945-1958).
Hugh Stott Taylor (1890-1974) was born in Lancashire, England. He attended the University of Liverpool where he received his Doctorate in Science in 1914. While pursuing his graduate degree, Taylor completed research in the field of physical chemistry at the Nobel Institute in Stockholm, Sweden between 1912-1913 and the Technische Hochschule in Hanover, Germany in 1913-1914. Taylor came to Princeton University as a chemistry instructor and achieved full professor status by the age of thirty-two and later became the first David B. Jones Professor in 1927. His work in the field of physical chemistry, particularly catalysis, was widely recognized by the scientific community when in 1919 he coauthored, with Sir Eric Rideal, the first notable book on catalysis. As a result of his reputation in the field, Taylor was often called upon for consultation by government and industry and was active in several projects during the First and Second World Wars. He received numerous international honors over his lifetime, which include the Nichols Medal of the American Chemical Society in 1928 and Fellow of the Royal Society of London in 1932. In 1953 he was twice knighted, first by Pope Pius XII in the Order of St. Gregory the Great and then by Queen Elizabeth in the Order of the British Empire.
Taylor was chairman of the Chemistry Department at Princeton University from 1926 to 1951. Under his twenty-five years of leadership, Taylor successfully promoted the chemistry program and recruited great scientific talent to the university, significantly increasing enrollment. While serving as dean of the Graduate College between 1945 until his retirement in 1958, Taylor strengthened Princeton's graduate program by adding nine Ph.D. programs. Taylor also was active in his faith and assisted in establishing the Catholic chaplaincy at Princeton in 1928. He was president of Pax Romana, the international Roman Catholic movement for intellectual and cultural affairs, and a member of the Pontifical Academy of Sciences. In 1962 an anonymous donor provided an enduring memorial of Sir Hugh's lifelong contribution to Princeton with a $500,000 gift establishing the Hugh Stott Taylor Chair of Chemistry. Hugh Stott Taylor died on April 17, 1974.
The collection consists of articles, correspondence, and printed matter of Taylor, chairman of the Princeton chemistry department (1926-1951) and dean of the graduate school (1945-1958). The collection, for the most part, is comprised of offprints of articles by Taylor and others, but there are also chemistry notes, articles, and accompanying correspondence on catalysis for the Encyclopaedia Britannica, Collier's Encyclopedia, and Annual Review Of Physical Chemistry as well as a bibliography of Taylor's articles.
Collection is unprocessed but a small portion is arranged in this order: manuscripts, correspondence, bound articles, and offprints.
Collection is open for research use.
Please consult with Rare Books and Special Collections about having the collection recalled to Firestone Library for your use. This process normally requires 48-72 hours notice.
The collection was formed as a result of a departmental practice of combining into one collection manuscript material of various accessions relating to a particular author.
Gift of Mrs. Maurice Healy.
The following sources were consulted during preparation of biographical note: Leitch, Alexander. A Princeton Companion, (Princeton University Press, 1978) and Marquis Who's Who on the Web.
Princeton University. Dept. of Chemistry -- 20th century.; Catalysis.; Chemistry -- Study and teaching -- New Jersey -- Princeton -- 20th century.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Faculty papers.; Chemists -- New Jersey -- Princeton.; History of science; Princeton University
- Addresses, 1927-1963; 1 box
- Addresses, 1964-1974; portion of 1 box
- Addresses, undated; portion of 1 box
- Writings, 1933-1974; portion of 1 box
- Writings, undated; portion of 1 box
- Correspondence re Treatise on Physical Chemistry, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- 14 pp ms. of unknown work, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Religious perspective of college teaching - mimeo copy and material about misc. documents and notes mainly on chemistry, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Taylor - Eyring broadcast, 1945 December 30; portion of 1 box
- Graduate School miscellaneous papers, 1945-1958; portion of 1 box
- University Research Committee, 1924-1930; portion of 1 box
- Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship Foundation, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Miscellaneous material about HST, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Biography and bibliography by Charles Kemball - Royal Society obit, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Bibliography from Kemball bibliography, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1953-1974; portion of 1 box
- Correspondence and material about scientific work of H. Austin and Monica Taylor, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Correspondence with Joseph T. Brandt, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Jacques Maritain Trust Fund, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Writings of others, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Photos, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Pax Romana material. Correspondence with Maurice Wright. Awards, citations, diplomas, honorary degrees, etc., dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Pax Romana material, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Correspondence with Maurice Wright. Awards, citations, diplomas, honorary degrees, etc., dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Honorary degrees and awards, dates not examined; multiple boxes
- Catalysis: ms. and t.s., dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Reprinted articles from various scientific journals, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Hoods, dates not examined; multiple boxes
- Reprinted articles from various scientific journals, dates not examined; 1 box
- Offprints, 1911-1938; 1 box
- Offprints, 1939-1961; 1 box
- Offprints, 1962-1972; 1 box
- Pamphlet volumes, undated; 1 box
- Drawing and photo of Pontifica Academia Scientiarum, dates not examined; 1 box
- 32101040880807 (Box 1)
- 32101040880815 (Box 2)
- 32101040880823 (Box 3)
- 32101040880831 (Box 4)
- 32101040880849 (Box 5)
- 32101040880856 (Box 6)
- 32101040880864 (Box 7)
- 32101040880872 (Box 8)
- 32101040813725 (Box 9)
- 32101040813733 (Box 10)
- 32101040813741 (Box 11)
- 32101040813758 (Box 12)
- 32101040813766 (Box 13)
- 32101040880880 (Tube 1)